Guide to the Charles Claude Guthrie Publications, 1903-1948 UA.90.F103
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Charles Claude Guthrie Publications
1903-1948
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Guthrie, Charles Claude
UA.90.F103
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
This is a collection of the publications of Dr. C.C. Guthrie. These publications span from the beginning of his medical career to his retirement as a professor at the University of Pittsburgh.
Previous Citation
Charles Claude Guthrie Publications, 1903-1948, UA.90.F103, University of Pittsburgh Archives
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection of publications by C.C. Guthrie spans his career from 1903 to 1956. This includes his time spent as a professor of pharmacology and physiology at Washington University and the University of Pittsburgh, contributing to the understanding of blood vessels and grafted tissues.
Biography/History
Charles Claude Guthrie was born in Gilmore, Missouri, on September 26, 1880. He graduated in 1901 from the Universtiy of Missouri with a degree in medicine and earned his Ph.D. in 1908 at the University of Chicago. From there he became a professor of pharmacology and physiology at the University of Washington before moving to the University of Pittsburgh, where he remaineded until retirement. His work included the study of suturing blood vessels, resuscitation, and ungrafted tissues. He is also known for his work with Alexis Carrel regarding vascular surgery.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the University of Pittsburgh's Falk Medical Library on July 30, 2012. This collection was separated from the Falk Library Medical School History Collection (UA.2012.28) in March 2017.
Medicine, Experimental; Faculty papers; Medicine -- Research; University of Pittsburgh; Blood-vessels -- Surgery; Human physiology; Guthrie, Charles Claude
- List of Publications by C.C. Guthrie (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "The Laking of Dried Red blood-Corpuscles," American Journal of Physiology, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "The Influence of Formaldehyde on the Action of Certain Laking Agents on the Coagulation of Blood," American Journal of Physiology, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "An Improved Mercury Manometer" and "A Servicable Form of Capillary Electrometer," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "The Effect of the Intravenous Injection of Formaldehyde and Calcium Chloride on the Haemolytic Power of Serum," American Journal of Physiology, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "A Contribution to the Clinical Knowledge of Texas Fever," Journal of Infectious Diseases, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Science and the Newspapers," Science, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "The Effects of Intravenous Injections of Bone Marrow Extracts Upon Blood Pressure," American Journal of Physiology, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Functions of a Transplanted Kidney," Science, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- "Extirpation and Replantation of the Thyroid Gland with Reversal of the Circulation," Science, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- "The Transplantation of Veins and Organs," American Medicine, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Complete Amputation of the Thigh with Replantation," American Journal of the Medical Sciences, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Uniterminal and Eiterminal Venous Transplantations," Surgery, Gynocology and Obstetrics, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "Results of Replantation of the Thigh" and "Successful Transplantation of Both Kidneys form a Dog into a Bitch with Removal of Both Normal Kidneys from the Latter," Science, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "The Resuscitation of the Central Nervous System of Mammals," Journal of Experimental Medicine, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "A New Method for the Homoplastic Transplantation of the Ovary," Science, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "The Relation of Pressure in the Coronary Vessels to the Activity of the Isolated Heart and Some Clearly Related Problems," Science, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- "The Effect of Changes in Blood Pressure of Respiratory Movements," American Journal of Physiology, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- "The Maintenance of Cerebral Activity in Mammals by Artificial Circulation," American Journal of Physiology, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- "The Relation of the Activity of the Excised Mammalian Heart to Pressure in the Coronary Vessels and to its Nutrition," American Journal of Physiology, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- "Respiratory Valves," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- "Surgical Rooms of the Department of Physiology and Pharmacology," Quarterly Bulletin of the Medical Department of Washington University, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- "A Study of the Relative Efficienct of Various Solutions on the Activity of the Isolated Mammalian Heart," Quarterly Bulletin of the Medical Department of Washington University, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "Results of Transplantation of Ovaries in Chickens," Quarterly Bulletin of the Medical Department of Washington University, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- "Heterotransplantations of Blood Vessels," American Journal of Physiology, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- "Results of Removal and Transplantation of Ovaries in Chickens," American Journal of Physiology, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- "Futher Results of Heterotransplantations of Blood Vessels," Science, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- "Results of Heterotransplantations of Blood Vessels" (Box 1, Folder 28)
- "Futher Observations on the Relation Between Blood Pressure and Respiratory Movements," American Journal of Physiology, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- "Futher Results of Transplantation of Ovaries in Chickens," Journal of Experimental Zoology, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- "Studies in Resuscitation: I. The General Conditions Affecting Resuscitation, and the Resuscitation of the Blood of the Heart," Journal of Experimental Medicine, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- "Studies in Resuscitation: II. The Reflex Excitability of the Brain and Spinal Cord After Cerebral Anaemia," American Journal of Physiology, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- "Studies in Resuscitation: III. The Resuscitation of the Glands and Muscles After Temporary Anaemia," American Journal of Physiology, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- "Studies in Resuscitation: IV. The Return of Function in the Central Nervous System After Temporary Cerebral Anaemia," Journal of Experimental Medicine, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- "Control of Spasms by Asphyxiation," American Journal of Physiology, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- "Some Practical Aspects of the Physiology of the Circulation," Interstate Medical Journal, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- "Structural Changes and Survival of Cells in Transplanted Blood Vessels," Science, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- "Transplantation of Formaldehyde-Fixed Blood Vessels," Science, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- "Results of Ovarian Transplantation on Body Weight and Egg Weight in Fowls," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- "The Harmful Action of 'Physiologial' Salt Solutions on Animal Tissue," "Fate of Transplanted Blood Vessels," "Futher Results of Transplantation of Ovaries in Chickens," and "On the Relation of Circulation to Spasms," Quarterly Bulletin of the Medical Department of Washington University, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- "On Misleading Statements," Science, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- "Guinea Pig Graft-Hybrids," Science, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- "Suture of Blood-Vessels with Human Hair," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- "The Effect of the Kidneys of Temporary Anaemia, Alone and Accompanied by Perfusion," Archives of Internal Medicine, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- "The Effect of Asphyxia on the Pupil," Science, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- "Survival of Engrafted Tissues I. (A) Ovaries and (B) Testicles," Journal of Experimental Medicine, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- "Survival of Engrafted Tissues II. (A) Thyroid (Including Parathyroid) (B) Kidney (Including Adrenal)," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- "Survival of Engrafted Tissues III. Blood-Vessels," Heart, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- "The Action of Magnesium Salts: A. In Relation to Motor Nerve Impulses; B. In Relation to Sensory Stimulation," and "The Effects of Direct Application of Magnesium Salts: A. To Motor and Sensory Nerves; B. To Cardio-inhibitory Nerves," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- "The Survival and Growth of Subcutaneously Engrafted Ovarian and Testicular Tissue," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- "The Effect of Anemia and of Double Hyperemia on Hyperplastic Goitre," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- "On the Alleged Specific Anaesthetic Properties of Magnesium Salts," American Journal of Physiology, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- "On the Insufflation of the Lungs with Hydrogen; with Carbon Dioxide; and with Air," Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Theraputics, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- "Futher Observations on the Structure of Anastomosed Blood Vessels," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- "Intravenous Foreign Bodies," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- "Uber Ausschaltung der hoheren Zentren zu physiologischen Zwecken," Zeitschrift fur Biologische Technik und Methodik, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- "On Graft Hybrids," Annual Report to the American Breeders Association, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 57)
- "Alterations of the Circulation in Goitre," Interstate Medical Journal, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 58)
- "On Evidence of Soma Influence on Offspring from Engrafted Ovatian Tissue," Science, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- "Respiration Valves," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 60)
- "Transplantation of Ovaries," Science, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 61)
- "Vascular Suture and Some Consideration Regarding its Successful Execution and Application," Cleveland Medical Journal, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 62)
- "Physiology of the Heart," Pennsylvania Medical Journal, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 63)
- "What Mathmatical Subjects Should be Included in the Curriculum of the College?," The Mathmatics Teacher, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 64)
- "Weight Fluctuations in Frogs," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 65)
- "The Sensory Effect of Local Application of Hypertonic Salt Solutions," Proceedings for the Society of Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 66)
- "The Blood in 'Shock'," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 67)
- "Laking of Blood by Hypertonic Solutions," "Laking of Blood by Freezing and Thawing," and "Laking of Blood by Drying," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 68)
- "Ovarian Transplantation," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 69)
- "Contributions to Practical Physiology and Pharmacology," Published and Presented by Writer, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 70)
- "Muscular Irritability," American Journal of Physiology, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 71)
- "Digitalis on Cardiac Irritability," Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Theraputics, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 72)
- "Experimental Shock," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 73)
- "A Tentative Explaination of the Mechanism of Hemolysis Associated with Loss of Water, and the Bearing of the Phenomenon of Certain Biologic Problems," Journal of Labratory and Clinical Medicine, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- "The Interpretation of the Manifestations of Shock," Pennsylvania Medical Journal, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 75)
- "Observations in Shock," American Journal of Physiology, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 76)
- "The Blood in Shock," Archives of Internal Medicine, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 77)
- "End-Results of Arterial Restitution with Devitalized Tissue," Journal of the American Medical Association, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 78)
- "The Blood in Clinical Shock," American Journal of Physiology, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 79)
- "A Method for Determining the Rate of Oxygen Absorption by Blood," American Journal of Physiology, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 80)
- "Physiological and Physiological Chemical Observations in Epidemic Influenza," Monograph on Epidemic Influenza, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 81)
- "A Symplified Form of Apparatus for Air Analysis," Journal of Biological Chemistry, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 82)
- "A Simple and Accurate Metabolism Spirometer. Spirometer Measurements of Oxygen Consumption by the Rebreathing Method," Archives of Internal Medicine, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 83)
- "A Gas Receiver of Convenient and Practical Form for Sampling Expired Air for Analysis," Journal of Biological Chemistry, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 84)
- "A Spirometer for Continuously and Accurately Measuring Expired Air and Sampling for Analysis," Journal of Laboratory and Clinical Medicine, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 85)
- "Results on an Enlarged Thyroid Gland Nine Years After Obstructing the Veins," American Journal of Physiology, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 86)
- "End Results of Arterial Transplants," Annals of Surgery, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 87)
- "Twenty-Five Years Progress in Physiology and Pharmacology," Proceedings, Congress on Medical Education, Licensure, Public Health and Hospitals, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 88)
- "Respiration in Fowls," American Journal of Physiology, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 89)
- "Blood Gas Analyzer," Journal of Labratory and Clinical Medicine, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 90)
- "Studies on the Rate of Oxygen Absorption," Journal of Biological Chemistry, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 91)
- "Methemoglobinemia," Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Theraputics, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 92)
- "Refractory Period in Heart," American Journal of Physiology, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 93)
- "An Apparatus for Quickly Measuring the Specific Gravity of Body Fluids," Journal of Labratory and Clinical Medicine, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 94)
- "A Split Second Timer," Journal of Labratory and Clinical Medicine, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 95)
- "Protective Amputation of Limbs by Stagomantis Carolina," Science, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 96)
- "Swarming and Mating of Ants," Science, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 97)
- "Functional Heart Mechanisms," Proceedings of the Society for the Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 98)
- "Physiologic Lensless Spectacles," Archives of Opthamology, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 99)
- "Science and Religion," Published by Writer, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 100)
- "Cause and Prevention of a Type of Leg Deformity in Brooder Raised Chicks," Federation Proceedings, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 101)
- "The Quantitative Effect of Hemorrhage on Plasma Proteins," Federation Proceedings, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 102)
- Collected Publications by C.C. Guthrie, 1903-1948 (Box 2, Volume 1)
- Collected Publications by C.C. Guthrie, 1903-1948 (Box 2, Volume 2)